Mss.Rec.142 Mss.Rec.142
American Philosophical Society
Interviews with Frances Jack
1984-1985
Mss.Rec.142
American Philosophical Society
12.0 Tape(s)
Linguistic field recordings and interviews with consultant Frances Jack on Central Pomo language and culture. Includes elicitations of Central Pomo words and expressions (some untranslated), discussion of differences between different kinds of Pomo, folkloric stories, anecdotes about local healers, and description of domestic activities. Also includes interview and discussion in English about various healing practices and attitudes towards traditional beliefs.
12 sound cassettes (9 hr., 37 min.): analog, 1 7/8 ips, stereo.
Jack, Frances
Mithun, Marianne
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presented by Marianne Mithun in 1986 (Acc. 1986-lr. S-B). This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Acorns as food; Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Central Pomo language--Syntax; Christianity and other religions; Fish--Folklore; Health.; Language attrition--California; Pomo Indians--Fishing; Pomo Indians--Folklore; Pomo Indians--Medicine; Pomo Indians--Music; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Central Pomo terms for parts of the body, 1984; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:25; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Audiocassette) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.); Human body--Terminology; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs
  - Central Pomo terms for colors, 1984; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:23; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Colors, Words for; Hopland (Calif.)
  - Central Pomo terms for directions, 1984; 01-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:26; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Anthropological linguistics; Cardinal points; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.)
  - Central Pomo alphabet and terms for plants and animals, 1984; 01-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:28; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo Indians--Ethnobiology; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs
  - Central Pomo kinship terms, 1984; 01-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:35; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.); Married people; Pomo Indians--Kinship
  - Central Pomo example sentences for describing sickness, 1984; 01-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:14; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Central Pomo language--Syntax; Health; Hopland (Calif.)
  - Comparison of Pomo terms spoken in Hopland and Yorkville, 1984; 01-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:28; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.)
  - Central Pomo phrases, 1984; 01-08; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:15; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Central Pomo language--Syntax; Hopland (Calif.)
  - Central Pomo speech, 1984; 01-09; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:48; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Scope and Contents note
    Untranslated Central Pomo speech in two segments. May be a reading from a text. Contents of this program are not specified in the collector's documenation.
  - Central Pomo terms and phrases, 1984; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:40:07; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    First 14:00 consists of Central Pomo terms for plants, animals, and directions, most likely read from a list, with a small number of English equivalents given. Remainder of program consists of almost entirely untranslated Central Pomo words, phrases, and sentences. From 38:59 to 39:34 there is uncorrectable distortion originating from the RDAT copy of the recording.
    Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.)
  - Description of Pomo fishing and fish cooking, 1984; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:17; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Description given in Central Pomo, then in English. Central Pomo segment may contain additional material not given in English segment.
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo cookery; Pomo Indians--Fishing; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1984; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:13:47; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Central Pomo word and phrase lists with frequent English explanation of expressions and contextual usage.
  - Central Pomo story about a game between the sucker and the eel, 1984; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:29; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Story given in Central Pomo, then in English. Central Pomo segment may contain additional material not given in English segment.
    Anthropological linguistics; Catostomidae; Central Pomo language; Fish--Folklore; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo Indians--Folklore
  - Central Pomo story about a daughter who did not help her mother, 1984; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:10; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.); Mothers and daughters--Folklore; Pomo Indians--Folklore
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1984; 03-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:31; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Central Pomo words and phrases with occassional English identification. May include vocabulary from previous story on recording. See Related Recording.
  - Description of Pomo methods for preparing acorns for cooking, 1984; 03-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:16; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Acorns as food; Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo cookery
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1984; 03-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:39; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Unidentified Central Pomo words and phrases with related sounds. No English given. Contains uncorrectable low-level mechanical background noise.
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1984; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:41:00; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Consists of word lists and phrases in Central Pomo, with minimal English idenfication given. Much of the second half of program focuses on similar sounding phrases, and possible sound and syntax changes. Also includes description of caterpillar gathering and cooking, and discussion of homonyms. Severe, loud hum occurs at 18:24-18:28 and predominates at 22:29-23:31.
    Anthropological linguistics; Caterpillars--Food; Central Pomo language; Central Pomo language--Syntax; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo Indians--Social life and customs
  - Central Pomo words, phrases, and sentences, 1984; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:33:57; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
  - Description of other Pomo speakers and miscellaneous expressions, 1984; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:07:14; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Consists of anecdotes of other people known by the speaker who spoke Pomo in a different way, as well as English explanations of miscellaneous Central Pomo terms and expressions.
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.); Language attrition--California; Pomo Indians; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs
  - Conversation in Central Pomo and English discussion of Central Pomo expressions, 1984; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:15; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    The second Central Pomo speaker is not identified on the recording nor in the collector's documentation.
  - Discussion in English of Central Pomo expressions and conversation in Central Pomo, 1984; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:20:34; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    The second Central Pomo speaker is not identified on the recording nor in the collector's documentation. From 11:15 to 11:19 there are two loud, uncorrectable hums. The silent gap between these hums represents a 3-minute uninterrupted hum on the original recording that was edited out.
  - Discussion in English of history of local discrimination against Pomo Indians, 1984; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:56; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Alcoholics; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo Indians--Alcohol use; Pomo Indians--History; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs; Race discrimination--California
  - Conversation and anecdotes in English and Central Pomo, 1984; 05-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:28:44; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo cookery; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs; Romanies--California
  - A story about Squirrel and the dance contest, 1984; 05-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:24; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Story given in Central Pomo and English.
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Dance--Competitions; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo Indians--Folklore; Squirrels--Folklore
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1984; 06-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:23:42; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo Indians; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1985; 07-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:44; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Central Pomo word and phrase lists in with detailed English explanation of expressions and contextual usage.
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Central Pomo language--Syntax; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo Indians; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1985; 07-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:29:10; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
  - Interview with Frances Jack, 1985; 08-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:45:01; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Interview consists of anecdotes given in English of sickness, attitudes towards local, traditional, and Christian healing practices, religious beliefs, and attitudes towards indigenous beliefs and practices. Includes multiple anecdotes about sick women and notable local healers.
    Hopland (Calif.); Pomo Indians; Pomo Indians--Medicine; Pomo Indians--Religion; Pomo Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs
  - Anecdote about a sick woman's treatment by a local healer, 1985; 09-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:59; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Healers; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo Indians--Medicine; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs
  - Anecdotes about a local healer, 1985; 09-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:40; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Stories told in two sections, each given first in English then in Central Pomo.
    Central Pomo language; Healers; Hopland (Calif.); Pomo Indians; Pomo Indians--Medicine; Pomo Indians--Social life and customs
  - Story in Central Pomo, 1985; 09-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:35; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1985; 10-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:30:04; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Central Pomo word and phrase lists with frequent English explanation of expressions and contextual usage. Background hum throughout recording. Intermittent sound error from :50 through 2:05
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1985; 10-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:08:18; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Central Pomo word and phrase lists with frequent English explanation of expressions and contextual usage. Background hum throughout recording.
  - Central Pomo song with story about a dance competition in Oregon, 1985; 10-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:56; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Background hum throughout recording.
    Anthropological linguistics; Central Pomo language; Hopland (Calif.); Indians of North America--Dance; Pomo Indians--Music
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1985; 10-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:01; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Unidentified Central Pomo words and phrases. No English given. Background hum throughout recording.
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1985; 10-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:57; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1985; 11-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:29:21; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Central Pomo word and phrase lists with infrequent English explanation. Original recording played slightly fast. The sound has been digitally corrected with some distortion remaining.
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1985; 11-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:45; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Central Pomo word and phrase lists with occasional English explanation of expressions and contextual usage. Original recording played slightly fast. The sound has been digitally corrected with some distortion remaining.
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1985; 11-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:16:37; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Central Pomo word and phrase lists with occasional English explanation of expressions, contextual usage, and pronunciation. Original recording played slightly fast. The sound has been digitally corrected with some distortion remaining.
  - Central Pomo words and phrases, 1985; 12-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:42; Jack, Frances; Mithun, Marianne
    Untranslated Central Pomo words and phrases.